Richard Price Papers 1767-1790 Mss.B.P93 Mss.B.P93
American Philosophical Society
Richard Price Papers
1767-1790
Mss.B.P93
American Philosophical Society
90.0 items
The Welsh non-conformist minister Richard Price (1723-1791) was a moral philosopher and political and economic theorist whose ideas leant support to the American cause during the Revolution. Of broad and liberal mind, he was an integral member of the intellectual coterie surrounding William Petty, the Earl of Shelburne, and was a founding member of the Unitarian Church. Befitting a latitudinarian thinker, the range of Richard Price's correspondence is extremely broad, touching upon his rationalistic philosophy and dissenting theology, his political views on British politics, America and the American Revolution, the Constitutional settlement, the future of the United States, social reform, demography, prisons, and slavery. The ninety letters in the collection are arranged chronologically, with correspondents including Charles Chauncy (8 letters, 1772-1779), Benjamin Franklin (7 letters, 1775-1789), John Howard (11 letters and a biographical manuscript, 1770-1789), Thomas Jefferson (3 letters, 1785-1789), Benjamin Rush (8 letters, 1786-1790), and Edward Wigglesworth (3 letters, 1775-1786), as well as lesser known figures such as the reformer John Howard.
Price, Richard, 1723-1791
Related Archival Materials note
The Printed Materials department includes numerous editions of most of Price's major works, including:
Additional Observations on the Nature and Value of Civil Liberty, and the War with America (London: Printed for T. Cadell, 1777)
An Appeal to the Public, on the Subject of the National Debt (London: T. Cadell, 1772)
A Discourse on the Love of our Country: Delivered on Nov. 4, 1789 (London: T. Cadell, 1790)
An Essay on the Population of England (London: T. Cadell, 1780)
Observations on the Importance of the American Revolution, and the Means of Making it a Benefit to the World (London, 1784)
Observations on the Nature of Civil Liberty (London: T. Cadell, 1776)
Bibliography
Peach, W. Bernard, and D.O. Thomas, eds., The Correspondence of Richard Price, 3 vols. (1983).
Proceedings of the Massachusetts Historical Society, ser. 2, 17 (1903): 263-278.
African American History Note
Some correspondence relating to slavery in the Price Papers may be of interest to scholars of African American history.
APS also possesses copies of Price's influential work "Observations on the Importance of the American Revolution" (print collection) in which, among other things, he condemns slavery.
The Price papers contain Thomas Jefferson's response to this work (see above), complete with an analysis of how Price's antislavery message may meet with a mixed response from Americans.
Early American History Note
This collection contains a series of letters from Richard Price, a prominent English minister who was also a prominent supporter of the American Revolution. There are several letters that are written in code. Prominent correspondents include Thomas Jefferson, Benjamin Franklin, Benjamin Chauncy, and Benjamin Rush. Some Price correspondence also discusses his opposition to slavery.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Accessioned, 1951.
Scope and Contents note
Befitting a latitudinarian thinker, the range of Richard Price's correspondence is extremely broad, touching upon his rationalistic philosophy and dissenting theology, his political views on America and the American Revolution, the Constitutional settlement, and his interest in social reform. The ninety letters in the collection are arranged chronologically, with correspondents including Charles Chauncy (8 letters, 1772-1779), Benjamin Franklin (7 letters, 1775-1789), John Howard (11 letters and a biographical manuscript, 1770-1789), Thomas Jefferson (3 letters, 1785-1789), Benjamin Rush (8 letters, 1786-1790), and Edward Wigglesworth (3 letters, 1775-1786).
At the heart of the Price collection is 31 letters written to and from America during the Revolutionary crisis. Typical of these are the eight long and candid letters written by the firebrand Boston clergyman, Charles Chauncy, between 1772 and 1779. Presciently, Chauncy wrote in 1772 that politics had degenerated to such an extent that "The alternative now seems to be, a submission to slavery, or an exertion of our selves to be delivered from it," and predicting "that half a Century will so increase our numbers and strength, as to put it in the power of New England only to tell any Tyrants in Great Britain in plain english, that they will be a free people, in opposition to all they can do to prevent it." In these early letters (1774-1775), the revolutionary rhetoric, set within a solidly religious--if not millenarian--framework is distinctive, and the letters of Chauncy, John Winthrop, Ezra Stiles, and other New Englanders, provide a detailed view of the flashpoint of the Revolution at the moment of its ignition. Winthrop's extraordinary letter of June 6, 1775, provides a thorough recounting of Lexington and Concord and their aftermath.
For his part, drafts of several of Price's letters to America demonstrate the depth of his sympathy with the revolutionary struggle and his intellectual integrity in the face of a critical situation. Price derided the official response to the martial crisis in Massachusetts and remained committed to the revolutionary cause to the end, imaging himself in June, 1777, as standing "in the Situation of a Silent Spectator waiting with inexpressible anxiety the issue of one of the most important Struggles that ever took place among mankind."
The slightly more numerous post-Revolutionary letters concern adjustments to the new political process in America, life expectancy (see Edward Wigglesworth), Italy and prisons (John Howard), the ratification of the Constitution (Franklin, Rush, and Jefferson), the French Revolution (Jefferson), and the impact of Price's seminal Observations on the Importance of the American Revolution, in which, among other things, he condemned slavery. Jefferson's response to the pamphlet displays him at his ambiguous best, grasping at the twin horns of slavery and liberty. While opposition to the work would be strong in the south, Jefferson wrote, "Northward of the Chesapeake you may find here and there an opponent to your doctrine as you may find here and there a robber and a murderer, but in no great number, in that part of America, there being but few slaves, they can easily disencumber themselves of them, and emancipation is put into such a train that in a few years there will be no slaves Northward of Maryland." As for Virginia, he placed his hopes in the rising generation who "have sucked in the principles of liberty as it were with their mother's milk."
Biographical/Historical note
The son of a harsh Calvinist Congregational minister in the Welsh heartland, Richard Price followed in his father's footsteps in profession only, becoming a leading advocate of a liberal Christianity and a supporter of republican and revolutionary values. Born in 1723 in Glamorgan, Price was educated at a succession of dissenting academies before establishing himself as chaplain to Mr. Streatfield at Stoke Newington and filling in at a variety of dissenting pulpits in the vicinity of London. The door from this seemingly obscure position to greater achievement, however, opened through Price's formidable literary and intellectual skills.
In his first and most widely known work, Review of the Principal Questions in Morals (London, 1758), written the same year that he married Sarah Blundell and settled at Newington Green, Price pitted himself against the moral philosophy of Frances Hutcheson, arguing that morality is intrinsic to human action and that good and evil could be ascertained through reason and individual conscience alone, without the need to posit the existence of a separate moral sense. In later works such as Importance of Christianity (London, 1766), Price built upon this rationalistic moral edifice, rejecting the concepts of original sin and eternal punishment, further distinguishing his thought from orthodoxy. Together with his friend Joseph Priestley, Price became one of the preeminent spokesmen for "rational dissent" in the 1760s and 1770s, and his works found a wide readership. Through his endeavors he became an intimate correspondent of several of the leading intellectual figures in England and America, including David Hume, Benjamin Franklin, Mary Wollstonecraft, and the Earl of Shelburne. In testimony to his stature, Price was admitted to the Royal Society in 1765 and received a doctorate of divinity from Aberdeen in 1767.
Price's reputation was founded not only upon his contributions to moral and religious philosophy, but for his pioneering interest in finance, economy, and insurance. He published an important work on life expectancy in the Philosophical Transactions of 1769, and his pamphlet, "Appeal to the Public on the Subject of the National Debt" (London, 1771) lambasted the growth of the public debt, inducing William Pitt to make serious efforts toward its eradication. Among his other works, Observations on Reversionary Payments (1771) fleshed out a practical system for life-insurance and pensions, and his Essay on the Population of England (1780) was an important effort in its genre.
Politically and religiously, Price was a throughgoing liberal. During the American Revolution, he was one of the most strident and consistent voices in England opposing war against the Americans. His Observations on Civil Liberty and the Justice and Policy of the War with America (London, 1776) sold remarkably well, earning accolades and broadsides intermittently, and for this and the unqualified support he tendered the American cause, Congress invited him to emigrate in 1778 and assume responsibilities for overseeing American finances. Price wisely declined. After the war, his popularity soared on both sides of the Atlantic, but his health soon failed. He lived to see the United States lay the foundation of its political organization with the ratification of the Constitution and to witness the early, optimistic phases of the Revolution in France, a "glorious" one in his eyes, without experiencing either the depths of French Revolutionary violence or the English backlash against political and religious unorthodoxy. A founding member of the Unitarian Society in 1791, Price died on the twenty-fifth anniversary of Lexington and Concord, April 19, 1791.
Bingham, William; Bowdoin, James, 1726-1790; Chauncy, Charles, 1705-1787; Clarke, John; Eliot, Samuel, 1739-1820; Foster, William; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Gordon, William, 1728-1807; Graves, Thomas Graves, 1st Baron, 1725-1802; Hazlitt, William, 1737-1820; Howard, John, 1726-1790; Ingenhousz, Jan, 1730-1799; Jackson, John; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Lansdowne, William Petty, Marquis of, 1737-1805; Lathrop, John, 1740-1816; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; Stiles, Ezra, 1727-1795; Sullivan, James, 1744-1808; Van der Capellen, Joan Derk, 1741-1784; Vaughan, Samuel, Sr., 1720-1802; Wheelock, John, 1754-1817; White, William, 1748-1836; Wigglesworth, Edward, 1732-1794; Willard, Joseph, 1738-1804; Winthrop, John, 1714-1779; Abolition, emancipation, freedom; African American; American Philosophical Society; American Revolution; Bunker Hill, Battle of, 1775; Colonial Politics; Ethics--Great Britain--Early works to 1850; France--History--Revolution, 1789-1799; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Gage, Thomas, 1721-1787; General Correspondence; Great Britain--Politics and government--1760-1789; Harvard College; Howard, John, 1726-1790; Italy--Description and travel--18th century; Lexington, Battle of, 1775; Life expectancy; Massachusetts--History--Revolution, 1775-1783; Pensions--Massachusetts; Political Correspondence; Prisons; Religion; Slavery.; Slaves, slavery, slave trade; Smith, Adam, 1723-1790; Smith, Isaac, 1744-1817; Social conditions, social advocacy, social reform; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Religious aspects; United States--Politics and government, 1783-1788
- Papers
  - Letter to Richard Price, Oct. 22, 1767; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Scope and Contents note
    A.L.S. 1p. Franklin quotes a favorable review for Price's "late work" as given in the Bibliotheque des Science des beaux Arts.
  - Letter to [Richard] Price, London, June 13, 1770; Howard, John, 1726-1790
    Rome, A.L.S. 4p. and add. Seal. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Garrulous letter of travels through Flanders, France and Italy. Ascent of Vesuvius.
  - Letter to Richard Price, Sept. 28, 1772; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    A.L.S. 2p.
  - Letter to Richard Price, Oct. 5, 1772; Chauncy, Charles, 1705-1787
    Boston, A.L.S. 4p. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from... B.Franklin.) Printed: Mass.Hist.Sec. Proceedings. Ser. 2, vol. 7, 265-266.
  - Letter to [Richard] Price, May 30, 1774; Chauncy, Charles, 1705-1787
    Boston, A.L.S. 4p. Enc. wanting. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Complains about the closing of Boston due to the port bill and of the acts against the rights of the colonists. Enclosed originally with letter from Charles Chauncy to Richard Price, July 18, 1774. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol. 7, 266-268.
  - Letter to Richard Price, July 18, 1774; Chauncy, Charles, 1705-1787
    Boston, A.L.S. 4p. Enc. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Concerning the united action of the colonists to help Boston against the port bill and rising tide of anti-British Sentiment. Enclosed originally with this letter was letter from Charles Chauncy to Richard Price of May 30, 1774. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol. 7, 268-270.
  - Letter to Richard Price, Sept.13, 1774; Chauncy, Charles, 1705-1787
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. Enc. wanting. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Introduces Josiah Quincy and discusses the rise of anti-British feeling in Boston due to the port bill. Printed: Mass. Hist. Soc. Proceedings. Ser. 2, vol. 7, 270-271.
  - Letter to [Richard] Price, Sept. 20, 1774; Winthrop, John, 1714-1779
    Cambridge, New England, A.L.S. 4p. End. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Mentions B.Franklin. Tells of state of Boston and Massachusetts due to the port bill. Says rebellion will occur if parliament does not back down. Introduces Josiah Quincy. Printed: Mass. Hist.Soc. Proceedings ser.2, vol.7, pp. 271-273.
  - Letter to [Richard Price], Dec. 26, 1774; Lansdowne, William Petty, Marquis of, 1737-1805
    Bowood Park, A.L.S. Shelburne. 4p. Enc. wanting. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from ...B.Franklin.) Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. Ser. 2, vol. 7, 273-274.
  - Letter to Richard Price, Jan. 10, 1775; Chauncy, Charles, 1723-1791
    Boston, A.L.S. 8p. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Discusses in detail the plight of Boston due to the port bill and the aid the colonies are rendering it. Comments on the continental congress. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol. 7, 275-278.
  - Letter to ----, Feb. 25, 1775; Price, Richard, 1723-1791
    Newington, A. draft of L.S. 8p. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Discusses political scene as it affects America. Praises B.Franklin. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol.17, 278-281.
  - Letter to Richard Price, London, April 10, 1775; Stiles, Ezra, 1727-1795
    Newport, A.L.S. 3p. and add. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B. Franklin.) Berates the expansion of Roman Catholicism in America. Says America will fight before surrending to Britain. Printed: Mass Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser.2, vol. 7, 281-283.
  - Letter to [Richard Price], April 10, 1775; Winthrop, John, 1714-1779
    Cambridge, New England, A.L.S. 4p. (see Richard Price Papers, Letters from...B.Franklin.) Introduces Francis Dana. Describes Boston and the aroused state of America, Mentions B.Franklin. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser.2, vol.7,283-286.
  - Letter to [Richard] Price, June 6, 30, 1775; Winthrop, John, 1714-1779
    New England, A.L. 6p. Enc. wanting. End. in shorthand. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Tells of the battles of Concord and Bunkers Hill. Mentions B.Franklin's arrival. Printed: Mass Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol. 7, 288-292.
  - Letter to Thomas Price, London, June 12, 1775; Wigglesworth, Edward, 1732-1794
    Cambridge, A.L.S. 2p. and add. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Speaks of Isaac Smith in laudatory terms Tells of the battles around Boston. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol. 7, 292-294.
  - Letter to Richard Price, London, July 18, 1775; Chauncy, Charles, 1705-1787
    Medfield, A.L. 12p. and add. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Talks of Josiah Quincy. Tells of the events of war around Boston, especially the battle of Bunker's Hill. Printed: Mass Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol. 7, 294-300.
  - Letter to [Richard Price], July 22, 1775; Chauncy, Charles, 1705-1787
    Medfield, near Boston, A.L. 3p. Mutilated. The signature appears to have been cut off. (see Richard Price papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. Ser. 2, vol. 7, 300-301.
  - Letter to [Richard] Price, London, Sept. 12, 1775; Gordon, William, 1728-1807
    Philadelphia, A.L. 3p. and add. End. Mutilated. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from ...B. Franklin.) Recapitulation of the hostilities between the U.S. and Britain. Mentions B.Franklin. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings, ser. 2, vol.17, 302-306.
  - Letter to --, Oct. 3, 1775; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    A.L.S. 4p. Franklin warns "... if you flatter yourselves with beating us into submission, you know neither the people nor the Country..."
  - Letter to [Charles Chauncy], Dec., 1775?; Price, Richard, 1723-1791
    [ca.] A.L. 3p. End. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Friendly letter. Mentions Dr. Priestley. Praises B.Franklin. Politics. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol.17, 306-307.
  - Letter to [Josiah Quincy], 1775; Price, Richard, 1723-1791
    [ca.] A.L. 2p. and scrap with French measurements reduced to English. End. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from... B.Franklin.) British attitude toward America. Praises. Dr.Franklin highly. Wishes for news for friendsof America in parliament. Printed: Mass. Hist. Soc. Proceedings. Ser. 2, vol.17, 286-288.
  - Certificate to Richard Price, March 14, 1776; London. Common Council
    London, D. 1p. Enc.: Miss Price's Papers. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from..B.Franklin.) Commending his publication of his Observations...
  - Letter to ----, May 14, 1776; Price, Richard, 1723-1791
    A.L. 2p. Enc. wanting. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) English public opinion. Would like to hear from "Dr. F[rankli]n" and other friends.
  - Letter to [Richard Price], April 20, 1777; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
    Paris, A.L.S. 8p. End. (see Richard Price papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Concerning the rupture between Britain and the U.S. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol. 7, 308-310.
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Franklin, Paris, June 15, 1777; Price, Richard, 1723-1791
    Newington Green, A.L. 1p. and add. Enc. wanting. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) High regards to B.Franklin. British feel sure America is almost won. Some plans for America from London. Printed: Mass. Hist. Soc. Proceedings. Ser. 2, vol.17, 310.
  - Letter to Arthur Lee, Paris, June 15, 1777; Price, Richard, 1723-1791
    Newington Green, A.L. 2p. and add. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Returns his thanks and asks for information. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol.17, 310-311.
  - Letter to [John] Winthrop, New England, June 15, 1777; Price, Richard, 1723-1791
    London, A.L. 2p. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Thanks for letters and news. Prudence requires his keeping quiet. Cannot even write B.Franklin. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol.17, 311-312.
  - Letter to [Richard Price], Dec. 14, 1777; Capellen, Joan Derk van der, 1741-1784
    Zwol, A.L.S. 7p. End. (see Richard Price papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. Ser. 2, vol. 7, 313-319.
  - Letter to [Richard] Price, London, March 24, 1778; Greaves, Thomas
    Rotterdam, A.L.S. 2p. and add. End. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Asks for advice on economic security of Britain.
  - Letter to [Richard Price], Dec. 8, 1778; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792
    A.L.S. 4p. End (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from... B.Franklin.) Asks aid in drafting a constitution for the U.S. and asks him to move to America.
  - Letter to [Richard Price], May 20, 1779; Chauncy, Charles, 1705-1787
    Boston, A.L. 3p. End. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from... B.Franklin.) Sends news of the state of affairs in the colonies. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol. 7, 319-321.
  - Letter to Richard Price, Feb., 1780; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Letter copy. 2p. Extract of a letter to Price in which Franklin lamented the "unhappy war" which he fears will remain unsolved in his lifetime.
  - Letter to Richard Price, June 13, 1782; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
  - Letter to James Hutton, July 7, 1782; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Extract of A.L.Cy. 2p.
  - Letter to Richard Price, London, Oct. 19, 1784; Hazlitt, William, 1737-1820
    Boston, A.L.S. 3p. and add. Slightly mutilated. End. in shorthand. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B. Franklin.) Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. Ser. 2, vol. 7, 322-324.
  - Letter to Richard Price, London, Jan. 25, 1785; Wheelock, John, 1754-1817
    Dartmouth College, A.L.S. 3p. and add. End. in shorthand. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Thanks for his contribution to the college. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser.2, vol. 7, 324-325.
  - Letter to Richard Price, London, April 11, 1785; Clarke, John
    Boston, A.L. 2p. and add. End. in shorthand, 2p. Incomplete. (see Richard Price Papers.) Letters from...B.Franklin.) Compliments him on his latest book.
  - Letter to [Richard] Price, Aug. 7, 1785; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    Paris, A.L.S. 2p. End. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from... B. Franklin.) Printed: Washington, Writings of T. Jefferson, I, 376-378.
  - Letter to [Richard Price], Aug. 8, 1785; Jackson, Jonathan, 1743-1810
    Boston, A.L.S. 3p. End. Contains notes in s shorthand. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from.. .B. Franklin.) Comments on Anglo-American relations and hopes to represent Britain in Boston. Mr. Adams is appointed minister to England. Printed: Mass. Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol. 7, 327-330.
  - Letter to Richard Price, London, Aug. 13, 1785; Wheelock, John, 1754-1817
    Dartmouth College, A.L.S. 2p. and add. End. in shorthand. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Thanks for his donation to the college. Comments on his pamphlets. Politics.
  - Letter to Joseph Williard, Oct. 6, 1785; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    A.L.S. 7p.
  - Letter to Richard Price, London, Nov. 15, 1785; Foster, William
    Boston, A.L.S. 1p. and add. End. in shorthand. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Sends him a cask of cranberries.
  - Letter to [Richard] Price, London, Nov. 15, 1785; Hazlitt, William, 1737-1820
    Hollywell, A.L.S. 3p. and add. End. Mutilated. (see Richard Price Papers. Letters from...B.Franklin.) Comments on the political scene in Penna and mentions John Vaughan and Benjamin Rush Settlers of Nova Scotia. Printed: Mass.Hist.Soc. Proceedings. ser. 2, vol. 7, 334-336.